[
    {
        "question": "Habitat loss and fragmentation, over exploitation, alien species invasion and co -extinction are causes for:",
        "correct_answer": "Biodiversity loss",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Biodiversity loss"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following never occurs during mitotic cell division?",
        "correct_answer": "Pairing of homologous chromosomes",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Cell Division"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the role of large bundle sheath cells found around the vascular bundles in C 4 plants?",
        "correct_answer": "To increase the number of chloroplast for the operation of Calvin cycle",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Plant Physiology"
    },
    {
        "question": "Select the incorrect statement regarding synapses:",
        "correct_answer": "Impulse transmission across a chemical synapse is always faster than that across an electrical synapse.",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Cell Structure and Function"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following stages of meiosis involves division of centromere?",
        "correct_answer": "Anaphase II",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which among the following are the smallest living cells, known without a definite cell wall, pathogenic to plants as well as animals and can survive without oxygen?",
        "correct_answer": "Mycoplasma",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Cell Structure and Function"
    },
    {
        "question": "Evolutionary history of an organism is known as :",
        "correct_answer": "Phylogeny",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Genetics and Evolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "Capacitation occurs in",
        "correct_answer": "Female Reproductive tract",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "Among the following characters, which one was not considered by Mendel in his experiments on pea?",
        "correct_answer": "Nature of trichomes i.e., glandular or non-glandular was not considered by Mendel.",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Genetics and Evolution"
    },
    {
        "question": "In water hyacinth and water lily, pollination takes place by :",
        "correct_answer": "Insects or wind",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "Identify the correct set of statements:",
        "correct_answer": "(1) (b), (c), (d) and (e) Only",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Plant Anatomy"
    },
    {
        "question": "Given below are two statements : one is labelled as Assertion (A)  and the other is labelled as Reason (R) . \nAssertion (A):  \nOsteoporosis is characterised by decreased bone mass and increased chance of fractures.  \nReason (R):  \nCommon cause of osteoporosis is increased levels of estrogen.  \nIn the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate  answer from the options given below.  \n(1) (A) is correct but (R) is not correct  \n(2) (A) is not correct but (R) is correct  \n(3) Both (A) and (R) are correct and (R) is the correct explanation  of (A)  \n(4) Both (A) and (R) are correct but (R) is not the correct explanation of (A)  \nAnswer ( 1) \nSol. Option (1) is the correct answer as osteoporosis is due to decreased levels of oestrogen.   \n Osteoporosis is an age -related disorder characterised by decreased bone mass hence, the chances of  \nfractures increase.",
        "correct_answer": "Option (1) is the correct answer as osteoporosis is due to decreased levels of oestrogen.",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "Praying  mentis  is a good example  of :",
        "correct_answer": "mullerian  mimicry",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Diversity in Living World"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following plants does not show plasticity?",
        "correct_answer": "Maize",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Diversity in Living World"
    },
    {
        "question": "What type of placentation is seen in sweet pea?",
        "correct_answer": "Axile",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Not Available"
    },
    {
        "question": "Bowman's glands are found in:",
        "correct_answer": "olfactory epithelium",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Structural Organization in Plants and Animals"
    },
    {
        "question": "Given below are two statements:  Statement I :  The release of sperms into the seminiferous tubules is called spermiation.  Statement II :  Spermiogenesis is the process of formation of sperms from spermatogonia.  In the light of the above statements, choose the most appropriate  answer from the options given below :  - 65 -  (1) Statement I  is correct but Statement II  is incorrect (2) Statement I  is incorrect but Statement II  is correct (3) Both Statement I  and Statement II  are correct (4) Both Statement I  and Statement II  are incorrect",
        "correct_answer": "Statement I  is correct but Statement II  is incorrect",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "W hich of the following is made up of dead cells?",
        "correct_answer": "Phellem",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Plant Anatomy"
    },
    {
        "question": "The correct sequence of phases of cell cycle  is :",
        "correct_answer": "G1  S  G2 M",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Cell Division"
    },
    {
        "question": "The infectious stage of Plasmodium that enters the human body is",
        "correct_answer": "Sporozoites",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Not Available"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following is present between the adjacent bones of the vertebral column?",
        "correct_answer": "Cartilage",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Not Available"
    },
    {
        "question": "Zygotic meiosis is characteristic of",
        "correct_answer": "Chlamydomonas",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "Match List -I with List -II. List-I List-II (a) Metacentric chromosome (i) Centromere situated close to the end forming one extremely short and one very long arms (b) Acrocentric chromosome (ii) Centromere at the terminal end (c) Submetacentric (iii) Centromere in the middle forming two equal arms of chromosomes (d) Telocentric chromosome (iv) Centromere slightly away from the middle forming one shorter arm and one longer arm Choose the correct answer from the options given below : (1) (a)-(ii), (b) -(iii), (c) -(iv), (d)-(i) (2) (a)-(i), (b) -(ii), (c) -(iii), (d) -(iv) (3) (a)-(iii), (b) -(i), (c) -(iv), (d) -(ii) (4) (a)-(i), (b) -(iii), (c) -(ii), (d) -(iv) Answer (3) Sol. In metacentric chromosome, centromere is in the middle of the chromosomes. Acrocentric chromosome has c entromere close to the end of the chromosome. In submetacentric chromosome, centromere is slightly away from the middle of the chromosome. Telocentric chromosome has terminal centromere. - 53 - ZOOLOGY SECTION -A",
        "correct_answer": "(a)-(iii), (b) -(i), (c) -(iv), (d) -(ii)",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Cell Biology"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which of the following statements is incorrect ?",
        "correct_answer": "Cyclic photophosphorylation involves only PS I.",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Photosynthesis"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following statements is correct ? - 67 -",
        "correct_answer": "Blood moves freely from atrium to the ventricle during joint diastole.",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Reproduction"
    },
    {
        "question": "While explaining interspecific interaction of population, (+) sign is assigned for beneficial interaction, ( –) sign is assigned for detrimental interaction and (0) for neutral interaction. Which of the following interactions can be assigned (+) for one species and ( –) for another species involved in the interaction?",
        "correct_answer": "Predation",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Not Available"
    },
    {
        "question": "Presence of plants arranged into well defined vertical layers depending on their height can be seen best in",
        "correct_answer": "Tropical Rain Forest",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Diversity in Living World"
    },
    {
        "question": "I dentify the vertebrate group of animals characterized by crop and gizzard in its digestive system",
        "correct_answer": "Aves",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Diversity in Living World"
    },
    {
        "question": "Which one of the following never occurs during mitotic cell division?",
        "correct_answer": "Pairing of homologous chromosomes",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Cell Structure and Function"
    },
    {
        "question": "What is the role of large bundle sheath cells found around the vascular bundles in C4 plants?",
        "correct_answer": "4",
        "user_answer": "Not Answered",
        "chapter": "Plant Physiology"
    }
]